Chapter 5. The American R. The tongue doesn't touch anywhere. Growl out the R in
the throat. American English today, although continually changing, is made up
of the sounds of the various people who have come to settle here from many
countries. All of them have put in their linguistic two-sense, the end result being
that the easiest way to pronounce things has almost always been adopted as the most
American. R is an exception, along with L and the sounds of a and th, and is one of
the most troublesome sounds for people to acquire. Not only is it difficult for
adults learning the language, but also for American children who pronounce it like a
w or skip over it altogether and only pick it up after they've learned all the other
sounds. The invisible R. The trouble is, you can't see an R from the outside. With
a P, for instance, you can see when people put their lips together and pop out a
little puff. With R, however, everything takes place behind almost closed lips back
down in the throat, and who can tell what the tongue is doing? It's really hard to
tell what's going on if, when someone speaks, you can only hear the R sound,
especially if you're used to making an R by touching your tongue to the ridge
behind your teeth. So what should your tongue be doing? This technique can help
you visualize the correct tongue movements in pronouncing the R. 1. Hold your hand
out flat with the palm up, slightly dropping the back end of it. That's
basically the position your tongue is in when you say ah. So your flat hand will
represent this sound. 2. Now to go from ah to the er, take your fingers and curl them
into a tight fist. Again, your tongue should follow that action. The sides of
your tongue should come up a bit too. When the air passes over that hollow in the
middle of your tongue, that's what creates the er sound. Try it using both your hand
and tongue simultaneously. Say ah with your throat opened and your hand flat.
Then curl your tongue up and your fingers and say er. The tip of the tongue should
be aimed at a middle position in the mouth but never touching and your throat should
relax and expand. R, like L, has a slight schwa in it. This is what pulls the er
down so far back in your throat. Another way to get to er is to put a spoon on your
tongue and go from the e sound and slide your tongue straight back like a
collapsing accordion, letting the two sides of your tongue touch the insides of
your molars. The tip of the tongue, however, again, should not touch anything.
Now, from E, pull your tongue back toward the center of your throat and pull the
sound down into your throat, eeeerrrr. Since the R is produced in the throat,
let's link it with other throat sounds.